Henry Mosler
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Writings and Notes, circa 1860-circa 1900, Series 3:; (Boxes 2-3, 6; 0.4 linear feet)
  - By Others (Box 3)
    - Edited Galley of "Henry Mosler, Artist," by John L. Covington, 1895, (oversized material housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Poems by Authors B-F, circa 1860-circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Poems by Authors H-W, circa 1880s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Poems by Authors with Illegible Signatures/Unsigned, circa 1862-1884 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Edited Galley of "Henry Mosler, Artist," by John L. Covington, 1895, (oversized material scanned with Box 3, F5) (Box 6)
- Personal Business Records, 1869-1905, Series 4:; (Box 3; 4 folders)
  This series includes Library of Congress copyright certificates for Mosler's pictures Awakening of Love, The Dancing Lesson, The Light of the Cross, and Sharing the Breakfast, in addition to several life insurance receipts and Sara Mosler's will. Of particular note is a detailed account book of Mosler's personal and professional income and expenses from 1869-1892. There is a gap in the accounting from the end of 1878 to October of 1886 when it resumes with a note written by Mosler explaining that he has found it a "great error not to mark down carefully the daily expenses as it serves two or more purposes-it answers as a 'diary'" and also serves as "something to prevent paying the same bill twice."
  - Account Book, 1869-1892 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Library of Congress Copyright Certificates, 1900-1904 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Life Insurance Receipts, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sara Mosler's Will, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, circa 1860s-1929, Series 5:; (Box 3; 10 folders)
  The bulk of this series consists of news clippings, primarily about Mosler from American and French newspapers. Also found is a brochure about Mosler and a catalog of an 1897 exhibition of his paintings. Miscellaneous items include an 1887 menu of a "Diner offert a Monsieur Mosler par ses Eleves" from the cafe of the Hotel Del'Elusee.
  - Brochure About Mosler, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Catalog, Galleries of Pape Bros., Exhibition of Paintings by Henry Mosler, Artist (1897), 1897 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1880s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - News Clippings, circa 1880s-circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 1880-1883 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, 1883-1884 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - News Clippings, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings, 1890-1896 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - News Clippings, 1905-1929 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - News Clippings of Poems, circa 1860s-circa 1890s (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1856-1917, Series 6:; (Box 4, OVs 10-11; 0.5 linear feet)
  Artwork by Mosler includes an undated engraving, 4 sketches (1858, 1893, 1898 and undated), a pencil sketch of Sara Mosler on her deathbed in 1903 dedicated to Mosler's children, and an ink drawing for Edith Mosler on her birthday in 1903. Also found are an oil portrait on a scallop shell; an 1890s book that contains sketches by Mosler and various artists including James Henry Beard, E. L. Ravenshaw, Lillian Greene and L. C. Mitchell; and an autograph book belonging to Edith Mosler, 1885, containting sketches by Mosler and others.
  Artwork by others includes a handwritten menu with a watercolor illustration signed by Garbriel Ferrier, J. Whitelaw Reid and others, a circa 1880 ink drawing by Leon Germain Pelouse; and an ink drawing of soldiers by E. Hillery.
  - Artwork by Mosler (Box 4)
    - Etching and Sketches, 1856-1903, (oversized material housed in OV 11) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Oil Portrait on Scallop Shell, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sketchbook, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Artwork by Mosler and Others, Autograph Book of Sketches, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artwork by Mosler and Others, Sketchbook, 1890s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1880s-circa 1900, (oversized material housed in OV 10) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others, circa 1880s-circa 1900, (oversized material scanned with Box 4, F6) (Box OV 10)
  - Oversized Artwork by Mosler, Etchings and Sketches, circa 1856-1903, (oversized material scanned with Box 4, F1) (Box OV 11)
- Photographic Material, 1860-circa 1910, Series 7:; (Boxes 5-9, BV 12; 2.0 linear feet)
  Photos of Mosler include two of Mosler in his studio, including an 1860 photograph taken in Cincinnati, one photo of Mosler in his studio with a group of students, and an early small framed head portrait.
  Photos of family include photos of Mosler and his wife, children, and grandchildren in 2 dismantled albums and 1 bound album. Album 2 also contains a 1906 pencil sketch by Mosler dedicated to Gustave and a watercolor sketch. Photos of others include artists such as Gabriel Ferrier, Ernest Hébert, and Thomas Buchanan Read, art critic Gustave Ollendorf, opera singers Emma Nevada Palmer and Renée Richards, and General R. W. Johnson, who appointed Mosler as aide-de-camp in the Civil War.
  Photographs of artwork include 2 albums dedicated to Edith Mosler and Gustave Henry Mosler respectively, containing photos of Mosler's paintings. The album dedicated to Edith also contains one photo of Mosler in his studio.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety with the exception of negatives and duplicates.
  - Photos of Mosler, 1860, circa 1870, circa 1890, (oversized material housed in Box 6) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photos of Mosler and Family (Box 5)
    - Mosler and Family, circa 1860s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - Album 1 Contents, 1860-1902 (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
    - Album 2 Contents, 1876-1906 (Box 5, Folder 8-11)
    - Album 3, circa 1860s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Glass Plate Negative Prints, circa 1860s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
    - Glass Plate Negative Copy Negatives, circa 1860s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photos of Others, circa 1860s-circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 16-19)
  - Photos of Others, "Munich Artists," Ambrotype, circa 1880 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Photos of Artwork by Mosler (Box 5)
    - "Album of Pictures by Henry Mosler to Edith Mosler," circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      (includes photo of Mosler; oversized material housed in Boxes 7-9)
    - "Album of Pictures by Henry Mosler to Gustave Henry Mosler," circa 1900, (oversized material housed in BV 12) (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Loose Photos, circa 1890-circa 1910, (oversized material housed in Box 6) (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Prints from Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1870s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Photos of Artwork by Others, circa 1870s-1900s (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Oversized Photo of Mosler, circa 1870, circa 1890, (oversized material scanned with Box 5, F1) (Box 6)
  - Oversized Loose Photos, circa 1890-1910, (oversized material scanned with Box 5, F23) (Box 6)
  - Oversized "Album of Pictures by Henry Mosler to Edith Mosler," circa 1900 (Box 7-9)
    (includes photo of Mosler; oversized material scanned with Box 5, F21)
  - Oversized "Album of Pictures by Henry Mosler to Gustave Henry Mosler," circa 1900, (oversized material scanned with Box 5, F22) (Box BV 12)